WHEN LIFE GIVES YOU TANGERINES
Well,
we have a house
and even a boat.
This is insane.
You happy?
Yeah.
I am, Gwan-sik.
Uh, stop!
It was our brightest season,
and it would never return.
LIFE GOES ON AND ON
HALLIM DISASTER RELIEF
DEPUTY CHIEF OH AE-SUN
BABY FORMULA
You've got to live up to your title.
Okay?
I'm the deputy chief, after all.
Let's just add two more.
Oh, for goodness' sake.
I told you I'd give you candy
after your food was done, didn't I?
Why don't you ever listen to Mommy?
- Goodness gracious.
- Mommy, give me a hug.
Give me a hug.
Mommy, I want a hug.
Mommy, Mommy, give me a hug.
Mommy! Mommy!
Ms. Oh! Ms. Oh!
Geum-myeong is in trouble! She's hurt!
- Mommy!
- What?
Mommy!
Is she bleeding? Tell me! Tell me!
I don't know. It's this way.
Auntie! Auntie!
Can you watch my kids for me?
Huh?
Are you the sea god's daughter? Are you?
Look, even the dolphins are running away.
How can you ride in a typhoon?
It's the motorbike that hit me,
not the other way around.
Jeju winds can flip over cars.
Your little bike here
would flip over again and again.
Gosh.
Auntie!
Where are the boys?
Are they sleeping in our house?
Huh? The boys?
Eun-myeong!
So why did you leave the boys behind?
It wasn't even a major accident.
- Eun-myeong. Honey! Oh no.
- Eun-myeong!
- Dong-myeong!
- Honey!
Dong-myeong!
Eun-myeong! Eun-myeong!
How many times did Grandma warn you
that once the boys start running,
they'll go anywhere, huh?
Hey, their shoes.
Their shoes are not here.
What?
I'll go look in the cabbage field and…
- Ae-sun, pay me for seaweed.
- …and, Mom, look around…
I didn't harvest all the seaweed
I was going to
because I found your biggest boy here.
Goodness gracious.
Oh!
I told you not to move and stay here,
didn't I?
He was standing alone on the seawall,
afraid and desperately looking for you.
Why did you leave?
Why did you go to
such a dangerous area alone?
The truck auntie would've come for you.
Why couldn't you just wait?
Why?
If you stand there,
the waves will swallow you up.
Cows get swept up by Jeju typhoons.
You have to be careful.
Where's Dong-myeong?
At home.
Wasn't Dong-myeong with you
this whole time?
He's home!
What are you telling me? Stop scaring me.
Mommy, give me a hug.
- Give me a hug. Mommy, I want a hug.
- Is she bleeding? Tell me. Tell me!
Mommy. Mommy.
Geum-myeong,
go call the chief's office.
Who can stop
the whims of summer?
Yesterday, it was bright and sunny,
like a bride on her wedding day.
And today, it gets aggressive
like when your wife loses her temper.
At least you can always get
a new wife…
…but when summer screws you over…
Goddamn it.
- Okay.
- Ow!
Oh man.
You can't build a barrier
by running your mouth, right?
Gwan-sik!
- Honey! Dong-myeong!
- Dong-myeong!
Dong-myeong!
Yang Dong-myeong!
- Dong-myeong!
Dong-myeong!
Where did he go? Dong-myeong!
Dong-myeong! Honey!
Yang Dong-myeong! Honey!
Where are you?
Dong-myeong!
Dong-myeong! Yang Dong-myeong!
Please have mercy on us.
Please, dear Lord.
Whatever it takes,
save the child for us, dear Lord.
Just save my grandchild.
Send our baby back to us.
Please save the child. Please.
It only takes a second to lose a child.
Please save him. Save my grandbaby.
Do you know what people
all over the world say
at any time they lose their kids?
- Dong-myeong! Honey!
- They all say the same thing.
"It happened in the blink of an eye."
They lost their child
in the blink of an eye.
They found my son? Did they?
Ae-sun.
Did we find my son?
What?
Hospital.
Dong-myeong needs to see the doctor.
Oh boy.
My baby, he's cold.
Why isn't anyone calling an ambulance?
Dong-myeong.
Honey.
Dear.
Dong-myeong.
Baby.
What's wrong with you?
Honey.
We need
to call the doctor. The doctor.
Call for an ambulance, okay, Gwan-sik?
Why
won't anyone call for the ambulance?
Just call for the ambulance,
why don't you?
It was the day
their world crashed down.
For the first time…
…their Steelheart broke apart.
My father's tears
filled the seas.
I should've hugged him.
Her son,
who was with her at lunch,
was no more by dinner.
Mommy. Mommy!
Mommy, give me a hug.
Give me a hug.
Mommy, I want a hug.
Mommy, Mommy, give me a hug.
I should've hugged him.
At the funeral,
Grandma never accused Mom of anything.
She just said that a mother
who lost her child
has more tears than the sea.
Move on.
What choice do you have?
You have two children
who still need you to be their mother.
Life will move on if you let it.
Life goes on.
There will be days when life is hard.
Once in a while, there may be days
you feel like
giving up on life altogether.
I said stop talking!
I won't agree to that!
I won't eat the abalone!
Oh, my little girl.
When will you understand?
Ae-sun,
if you ever feel like giving up on life,
think about my life as a haenyeo.
People who make their living on land
say they want to die so easily
when things get rough.
No matter how upset or agonizing life is,
they can't speak lightly of death
in front of a haenyeo.
I've faced death hundreds of times
in those powerful waters,
and each time, I found
hundreds of reasons to keep living.
So keep on living.
Keep on living.
Why die with so many reasons to live?
When your body's tired
and your heart wants to give up,
there will be days
when you want to give up on life.
Refuse to back down.
Fight to pick yourself back up.
Take out a blanket and stomp on it.
Till your soil.
Go earn your money.
If you tell yourself,
"I won't die. I'm gonna survive,"
and use your arms and legs to push you up,
you'll get past the dark waters
and finally see the sky.
By then, you'll breathe again.
- Do you know how to do it?
- No, I don't.
This will be sweet, right?
Ooh.
Ooh, it looks yummy.
Is that what you wanted to eat?
Is that the food you craved?
Hey, speak to me. What's going on?
Are you mad at Mommy?
Yang Eun-myeong.
I asked you why you won't talk to me, son.
Never gonna talk to me again, is that it?
SCHOOL SUPPORT FEES DUE BY THE 20TH
Why didn't you say
you got a perfect score?
Why'd you keep it a secret from me, honey?
Geum-myeong.
Hey.
Are you mad at Mommy?
So mad you won't say anything?
Is it because…
is it because…
…I didn't save your little brother?
Are you mad at me?
Is that why you're not talking?
It's because you are mad at me, Mom.
What?
I left my brother alone.
That's why he's dead.
It's 'cause…
it's 'cause
I went out there on the bike.
If I never left to ride the bike,
Dong-myeong would still be alive.
It's 'cause
I wouldn't listen when I was told not to
because a typhoon was coming.
Dong-myeong died
because I still went to go riding.
That was when
Mom and Dad
came to their senses.
I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
It's all my fault.
I'm sorry, Eun-myeong.
I'll do it.
The Steelheart
picked himself up after three days.
He finished his breakfast
and went out to sea.
Hmm.
Geum-myeong, tell your teacher
I'll pay your school fees
in three days, okay?
Hmm?
They had three days
to mourn. That's all.
Only three days.
Dad,
what are you gonna catch today?
Croaker.
Summer croaker.
- Croaker?
- Mm.
I'll bring them home
instead of selling them.
- Bring them back?
- Yeah.
Let's
all eat together tonight.
Let's all eat together as a family.
Wanna come eat with us?
She sold everything.
She's packing up.
Well, she has her back to the sea,
but business is good.
She says that
she doesn't want to even look at the sea.
The skies are so clear today.
Seeing it this clear,
as if nothing ever happened,
makes her want to vomit.
Her mother, her father,
and now the sea takes her son.
Imagine how she feels
earning a living at the sea.
Goddamn.
She has to live
with all of that heartache.
The sea god is a sadistic one.
He stole everything she held dear
but tells her,
"I'll keep you alive, I think."
So he still gives her all kinds of things.
I'm thankful to her.
I'm thankful she's moving on.
Did you sell all the squid?
We managed to catch
a convict grouper today.
If we sell that one,
we can get 1,000 won, easy.
We can even buy Eun-myeong a new backpack.
It's so unfair.
So unfair.
Geum-myeong. Eun-myeong. Let's go.
I don't wanna be
around the sea for any reason at all.
It's so unfair.
Ae-sun,
let's stop crying.
If Mom and Dad keep crying,
it'll affect the kids.
They'll always be anxious.
I want this summer to be over already.
Pretty annoying how erratic it is.
If it's hot, it's way too hot.
When it rains, it pours.
Summer lets nature grow lush,
but the next thing you know,
it brings storms and crushes everything,
and we're helpless.
The two-faced summer
brought my young parents
down to their knees.
Why does it have to be so aggressive?
If it were me, I'd cut me some slack.
Hey, watch out for that hole there.
No problem.
We all give beginners a break.
But it's a first for me too.
Why am I not getting a break
from the sea god?
Like grass
that was pressed down by the typhoon…
How can we move on now?
…she was knocked down,
but she got back up again.
Still,
life goes on despite the summer's whims.
Grass and trees that are knocked down
by the summer typhoon,
they'll get up again.
Rain can fall
and just sweep away everything.
Ah, but once the sun shines again,
everything comes back to life.
All things on land and sea.
What if I can't move on?
I think moving on
could be a thing I can't do.
There are crabs here.
Our kids need to live on.
- Where?
- Here.
You can't catch that one.
Gwan-sik.
I have caused it all.
I was the one who put…
Dong-myeong on the seawall.
On his first birthday,
I carried him on my back or in my arms
so we could all meet you on that seawall.
I lined up the kids and told them,
"If we stand up here, Dad will come soon."
I said no matter how bad the storm is…
you would return to us if we waited there.
I told them that.
Our baby, Dong-myeong…
…died because of me.
It's all my fault.
If you have to assign blame,
then look to the heavens and sea instead.
It's not your fault at all.
Hmm?
Look, nobody in our family
is to blame. No one.
Dad kept telling himself
no one was to blame,
but on the inside, he did resent someone.
Mom said she found out
who it was Dad resented
about 30 years later.
Hey.
ENDOSCOPY CENTER
Do you know what it is your dad uttered?
Um, he muttered nonsense or what?
People do that in endoscopy.
What, did he talk about
another woman?
Barrier.
Huh? Barrier?
Gwan-sik!
He was muttering the words,
"I shouldn't have gone
to build the barrier."
"I shouldn't have gone."
He's very much like steel
in every way.
Once something truly gets into the man,
he just locks it inside.
I don't know how he coped with it.
How did he cope with all that?
Should he have packed it in?
Uh-uh, there were still
two pairs of twinkling eyes watching us.
So we saved both you and Dad?
Absolutely, you did.
You did save us.
If it weren't for you…
If it weren't you…
NAME OF THE DECEASED: YANG DONG-MYEONG
HOUSEHOLDER: YANG GWAN-SIK
RELATIONSHIP TO HOUSEHOLDER: SON
DATE OF BIRTH: SEPTEMBER 6, 1974
3 YEARS OLD
You can't imagine
what it feels like to lose a child.
He couldn't cry openly anywhere.
He was completely broken on the inside.
Dalgona doesn't have much nutrition.
I ate my food. I promise I did.
Jeez, here.
Oh,
I wondered how we could move on.
What in the world did he eat?
Mom, I've been eating every day.
They even bring us meat most of the time.
We were able to move on
because there were people
who fed the children for us.
A canola flower never blooms by itself.
You always see a field of canola flowers.
Had I been on my own,
I would've been broken
a hundred times over.
You know,
as the saying goes,
it takes a village
to keep one person alive.
They're fine. They'll be fine.
With the stove on, they're okay, I think.
Don't make it too obvious.
They might not like
all that kindness and help.
Should we not give them those?
They're today's first eggs.
Give them the first eggs,
then they'll give them strength.
Don't keep me
from giving them eggs.
You're the one
who gave away all of our rice.
You gave them all our octopuses. You did!
So I was wondering
if I could get a little…
…rice, you know.
I don't understand.
What are you saying, dear?
What are you complaining about?
There's plenty of folks worse off.
But is it you?
The rice jar?
Well, I have no idea what you mean,
crybaby woman.
Why are you saying
you don't have any idea? I know you do.
'Cause, for some reason,
that empty jar is never completely empty.
I saw that the rice jar
was empty before I slept.
I know what I saw.
Every morning,
there's a little more, then a little more.
Hmm?
I thought maybe I didn't see very well
because it was night,
but it went beyond a day or two.
There's just enough for a family of three.
It's just so strange.
Just enough to keep us guessing.
It's the exact amount we need.
Oh, why do I bother?
Why do I bother?
It's not some magical jar,
and I'm not a dummy.
She got a migraine figuring it out.
If she just gave it to you,
you wouldn't take it, Ae-sun.
So then she really tried to give it
without you knowing about it.
Um, but… Well, if it gave her a migraine--
Who would want to watch
a pregnant woman go hungry?
Go steam the octopuses.
Somebody gave them to me.
You absolutely don't have to do this
for my mom's ancestral rites.
If you don't add octopus to her table,
your mom will come beat you down.
No haenyeo goes diving by herself.
When you're about to
lose your breath in the deep, dark waters,
well, you have got to be
very near other divers.
Otherwise, you won't be able
to breathe again.
No one's an island.
Let's go together.
If you go with others,
a hundred miles
will feel like ten miles, my dear.
GO TOGETHER, WITH OTHERS.
IF YOU DO, 100 MILES WILL FEEL LIKE TEN.
Gyeong-ja, that is Ae-sun's.
Ae-sun is having the baby soon.
I'm gonna give it to her.
I wanted to touch it a bit
because it has been a while,
so I just wanted
to feel it a little. There.
Right? They're pretty.
- Oh, she is something, isn't she?
- Hey, did you rinse this?
It's so cold.
Can you write
"For Moral Support"?
If you write that for me,
she'll definitely get it.
"For Moral Support," okay?
Hmm? Mm-hmm.
Works for you?
DO HUI-JEONG SCHOLARSHIP
10,000 WON
Is it wrong?
Three months of rent
to go to the baby's family, right?
Can you read, lady?
One, two, three, four.
One, ten, hundred, thousand.
Fine, yes.
Makes sense.
If only
I'd never hidden in that small closet.
Ah shit.
Why did you pay their rent, huh?
It's my destiny to live with
overly giving boss ladies, I guess.
Should you be saying that? Huh?
Sure, why not?
I deserve to be slapped
for what I've done back then,
but you're not guilty of anything.
Since when is love a sin?
Just cut the nonsense
and straighten your priorities out,
all right?
There's nothing complicated about karma.
Animals bring up animals.
Nobles breed nobles, huh?
Kids inherit
their parents' imperfections exactly.
Min-ok, stop.
She must've really hated me.
Her adolescence was ruined
once I joined the family.
It's pretty sneaky of me to think
I can make it up to her with 10,000 won.
- I gave her a whole cabbage field, okay?
- Oh, that rock field, right?
That field of dog shit?
It was Ae-sun's small hands
that plowed that field.
And on top of that,
that field's original owner
was her mother, Byeong-cheol.
Min-ok.
Talk the shit you want,
but keep your conscience straight.
Yapping doesn't justify a thing.
Min-ok, I told you to quit it.
I'm getting angry.
Now that I've raised our kids,
you should've paid for all of
Ae-sun's college tuition
because she truly deserved it.
Ooh! Come on, yeah, college!
Go! Go! Go!
She can go now if she wants.
I'll pay for her,
even if I have to take out a loan!
Why would she go to college now?
How? By what means?
Hey, if she gets in,
I'll pay her tuition. Tell her!
Don't say anything if she doesn't get in.
She doesn't need college to be a captain,
a deputy chief, or anything like that.
If she goes to Seoul,
she'll only be cut down to size.
The best she'll get
is a doctorate.
She'll just drain the family's wallet.
All we'll do is hang banners around town
to show off which college accepted her.
I never saw the big deal anyway.
Hi, Geum-myeong.
Oh, oh, it's her.
Did you make it?
Did you not?
Oh, Mom.
If I didn't get in, who would?
Look, look, look!
"Yang Geum-myeong." It's written here.
Oh my God. Wow.
Hey! Sell the boat! Sell it!
You did it. You did it for real, honey.
I… don't know
if it's okay for me to say this.
I never
thought that I would say this ever again.
- I…
- You're glad?
Yes.
I'm feeling so happy.
So glad.
CERTIFICATE OF ADMISSION
Okay, one, two, three.
Ah!
BOARDING HOUSE AVAILABLE
AFFORDABLE ROOM FOR RENT
RENT NEAR SNU
AFFORDABLE ROOM
Geum-myeong! Geum-myeong!
Your daughter's name is Geum-myeong?
We have one in our family.
Your son's name is Geum-myeong?
Oh, no.
It's me.
I am Geum-myeong.
I'm Park Geum-myeong.
Oh!
Wow, what an interesting coincidence.
YALASHANG FILM CLUB
Should we get some noodles?
So what's your major, huh? What is it?
Oh, um, law.
Let's go have noodles. Hurry up.
Let's take the picture and just go.
Here. I can take it for you.
- If you all want to stand there.
- Ooh, that's nice of you.
Okay, you take ours, and I'll take yours.
Whose picture? Why are you taking theirs?
Let's take it. Come on.
Thank you.
Mm.
Here we go.
One, two, three.
Okay, I'll take one more.
Smile.
One, two, three!
I said I didn't like him.
I told you
I didn't like that guy at all, didn't I?
Why not?
Those weren't intended to be solo shots.
Park Geum-myeong's son
was hitting on Geum-myeong.
Hitting on her!
Okay, I'll take one more.
Okay, smile.
One, two, three.
Oh, so you feel annoyed now?
Hey, let's call Geum-myeong.
Why? You believe they ran off to Busan?
Why would they go to Busan?
Jeez.
You pulled someone else's daughter there,
and you won't let your daughter go?
Oh, I pulled you there?
Jeez, I think you might
have a heart attack
if she ever wanted to get married.
Why would she get married?
I'm telling you ahead of time.
I can't go tomorrow.
Oh.
That's fine.
You have class tomorrow.
No way I can get to Nonsan.
I can't.
Take your mom.
Mm.
It's fine.
Go with Oh Ye-rim.
Why would I go with her?
Anyway, I can't go. You know?
I get it.
- I'm saying I can't go.
- I said I get it.
Damn it, you don't get it.
Well, what do you mean?
What am I saying if I can't go?
Tonight is
our last night together.
Man, it means it's our last night!
Keep her in check.
Your daughter is just like you.
I swear I'm going to, damn it.
What's wrong with you?
A chip off the old block, Oh Ae-sun.
WHEN LIFE GIVES YOU TANGERINES
Sweetie.
That's nice, isn't it?
Mm.
Is it a lot more expensive
to live on higher floors?
They're full right now, she said.
You believe her?
Well, she's not a sweet talker,
but she's the eldest.
She's always too careful,
even if I tell her not to be.
Jeez.
Why do people in Seoul
have rooms in basements, you think?
Hmm. My heart would break
if my baby was forced to live there.
Will we be able
to sell the cabbage field?
Just leave the field.
But you believe it'll sell?
And stop selling things.
Why? You wanna keep it?
If we sell it all,
you'll have nothing left.
Jeez, your wife over your daughter, huh?
You know, looking back at it all,
those days were nice.
That was the best summer we had.
Everything was so new back then.
Even though it all felt
awkward and difficult,
it was all new and exciting.
I loved everything, you know.
First love,
our honeymoon…
our first house,
first boat,
first full net.
First child.
Having our first child.
Words escape me.
Still leave the cabbage field, Ae-sun.
Just leave the cabbage field.
That field is your reward
for surviving that summer.
I wondered how we could move forward.
But life really just went on.
Hey, Mom, look at this!
Life went on and on.
LIFE GOES ON AND ON
"IN THE HOPE THAT OUR ECHOES
WILL FLOW AND FLOW UNTIL THEY REACH YOU."